A Guide to the IAWA: International Archive of Women in Architecture Records, 1967-2008 (bulk dates 1985-2008)
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
IAWA: International Archive of Women in Architecture Records, 1967-2008, (Bulk, 1985-2008)
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms1985-021
15.5 cu. ft. 10 boxes, 1oversize folder, 1 tube box
The records of the International Archive of Women in Architecture (IAWA) consist of files created by IAWA founder Milka Bliznakov, various IAWA officers, and Special Collections archivists. Materials include founding documents, meeting minutes, newsletter information, correspondence with supporters and donors, and internal correspondence.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
The International Archive of Women in Architecture records were donated to Special Collections in 1998 and 1999 by Dr. Bliznakov. Other materials have been periodically donated by various IAWA Board Members over the years.
Historical Note
The International Archive of Women in Architecture (IAWA) was established in 1985 as a joint program of the College of Architecture and Urban Studies and the University Libraries at Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University (Virginia Tech). The purpose of the program is to document the history of women's involvement in architecture by collecting, preserving, storing, and making available to researchers the professional papers of women architects, landscape architects, designers, architectural historians and critics, and urban planners, and the records of women architectural organizations, from around the world. The IAWA collects this information to fill serious gaps in the availability of primary research materials for architectural, women's history, and social history research.
Scope and Content
The International Archive of Women in Architecture records encompass the founding of and day-to-day operations of the organization. Materials present include administration files (meeting minutes, bylaws, financial information), correspondence (internal and with potential donors), collection development files (policy developments, solicitation efforts), promotional material (newsletters, exhibits, conferences, and visiting speakers), and reference files. The collection ranges in date from 1967-2008 (bulk 1985-2008) and is divided into three series: Founder's Files, IAWA Center Files, and Archivist Files.
Arrangement
The International Archive of Women in Architecture is a joint program of the College of Architecture and Urban Studies (CAUS) and the University Libraries at Virginia Tech. The arrangement of the collection into three unique series: Founding Files, IAWA Center Files, and Archivist Files retains the original order of the records and organizationally preserves the separate functions provided by each member of the partnership.
Index Terms
Persons:
Bliznakov, Milka T., d. 2010; Dunay, Donna
Subjects:
Architects and community; International Archive of Women in Architecture (IAWA)
Occupations:
Architects.
Contents List
- Founder's Files, 1985-1996
  - Correspondence with potential donors, (10 folders) 1985-1996 (Box 1)
- IAWA Center Files, 1967-2008 Bulk, 1985-2008
  - Administrative, 1985-2007
    - Board of Advisors, 1985-2007
      - Annual Meeting, 1988-2007
        - 2nd Annual Meeting, 2 October, 1988 (Box 1)
        - 3rd Annual Meeting, 22 October, 1989 (Box 1)
        - 4th Annual Meeting, 31 October 1990 (Box 1)
        - 5th Annual Meeting, 13 November 1991 (Box 1)
        - 6th Annual Meeting, 8 November 1992 (Box 1)
        - 7th Annual Meeting, 7 November 1993 (Box 1)
        - 8th Annual Meeting, 6 November 1994 (Box 1)
        - [10th] Annual Meeting, [the group's numbering system skips here], 22 October 1995 (Box 1)
        - 11th Annual Meeting, 10 November 1996 (Box 1)
        - 12th Annual Meeting, 6 September 1997 (Box 1)
        - 13th Annual Meeting, 27 September 1998 (Box 1)
        - 14th Annual Meeting, [see 15th Annual Meeting for minutes of meeting], 19 September 1999 (Box 2)
        - 15th Annual Meeting, 10 September 2000 (Box 2)
        - 16th Annual Meeting, (3 folders), 21 October 2001 (Box 2)
        - 17th Annual Meeting, 6 October 2002 (Box 2)
        - 18th Annual Meeting, (2 folders), 14 September 2003 (Box 2)
        - 20th Annual Meeting, 30 October 2005 (Box 2)
        - 21st Annual Meeting, 15 October 2006 (Box 2)
        - 22nd Annual Meeting, 2007 (Box 2)
      - Executive Committee Minutes, (13 folders), 1988-2001 (Box 2)
      - IAWA Emeritus Advisors and Honorary Status, 2000 (Box 2)
      - IAWA Center, 2002-2005 (Box 2)
        - IAWA Center, Center/University Libraries Partnership, 2005 (Box 2)
      - Nominating Committee, (4 folders), 1997-2003 (Box 2)
      - General Administrative Files, (6 folders), 1985-1990; 2000-2004 (Box 3)
    - IAWA By-laws, 1989-2000 (Box 3)
    - IAWA Letterheads, 1989-1990, and undated (Box 3)
    - IAWA Mailing List, 1996 (Box 3)
  - Bliznakov Prize, (5 folders), 1999-2003 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1989-2004
    - 1997-2004 (Box 3)
    - Bliznakov, [to/from], 1989-2002 (Box 3)
  - Collection Development, 1985-2001
    - Collection development materials (Box 3)
    - Collection development policy, 1998-2001 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence with potential donors, (2 folders), 1985-1986, 1997 (Box 3)
    - Mailing, typical letters in english, French, German, Portuguese, and Spanish, (4 folders), 1985-1986, 1992 (Box 3)
    - Potential donors (Box 3)
  - Financial Records, 1989-2006
    - Financial Records, General, (3 folders), 1989; 2001-2006 (Box 3)
    - Appraisal of IAWA Collection, 2000-2001 (Box 3)
    - Center Annual and Financial Reports, 2000-2003 (Box 3)
    - Fundraising Ideas, 2001 (Box 3)
    - Individual Donations, (2 folders), 1991-1993, 2000-2005 (Box 4, Box 3)
    - Milka Bliznakov Endowment, 2004 (Box 4)
    - Sigrid L. Rupp Endowment, (2 folders), 1997-2005 (Box 4)
  - Grants, 1967-2002 (Bulk, 1988-2000)
    - Proposal manuals/applications, 1967-1978 (Box 4)
    - Core Research Proposal, [to establish a resource center and organize Friends of the IAWA group], 1988 (Box 4)
    - Diversity Incentive Grants Committee, 2002 (Box 4)
    - Getty Grant Program, 2000 (Box 4)
    - Graham Foundation for Advance studies in the Fine Arts [for conference “Challenges of the Past and Future: And International Conference of the Contribution of Women to the Architecture of the 20th century], 1991 (Box 4)
    - MB Grant [for computerized central information system of works by women architects and landscape architects] (Box 4)
  - Newsletters, (20 folders), 1989-2008 (Box 4)
    - Mailing List (Box 4)
    - Production of Newsletter, 1990 (Box 4)
    - Production of Newsletter, 10th Anniversary of IAWA, 1995 (Box 4)
    - Production of Newsletter, (4 folders), 1998-2001 (Box 4)
    - Responses, (8 folders), 1990-1992, 1994-1999 (Box 4, Box 5)
  - Presentations, 1984-2007
    - Exhibits -- America tours for "History of Women Architects" German Federal Republic and "Women Architects in Austria, 1900-1987" Austrian Cultural Institute, 1984-1986 (Box 5)
    - Audio Recording: "Women in Design," Cowgill Hall, (3 cassettes), May 1985
    - Conference -- The Invisible Partner: 2nd symposium on Women in Design and Architecture, October 28-November 3, 1986 (Box 5)
    - Conference -- "Challenges of the Past and the Future: An International Conference of the Contribution of women to the Architecture of the 20th Century," 1991 (Box 5)
    - Exhibit -- "Contribution of Women architects to the Man-Made Environment," Wallace Hall Gallery, brochures, 17 March-4 April 1997 (Box 5)
    - Exhibit -- IAWA Exhibit Placards, September 1997 (Box 5)
    - Exhibit -- "Lois Gottlieb: Continuing the Legacy of Frank Lloyd Wright," Wallace Hall Gallery, 16 March-3 April 1998 (Box 5)
    - Visiting Speaker -- Anne Tyng, (2 folders), March 18-22, 1999 (Box 5)
    - Exhibit -- IAWA Fall Exhibit, 1999 (Box 5)
    - Visiting Speaker -- Brinda Somaya, October 18, 2001 (Box 5)
    - Visiting Speaker -- Yasmeen Lari, October 5-6, 2002 (Oversize Folder 1, Box 5)
    - Exhibit -- 20th Anniversary Exhibit, 2005 (Box 5)
    - Symposium -- "Honoring Women in Architecture and the Related Design Fields from last century to 2006, 2006 (Oversize Folder 1)
    - Visiting Speaker -- Anna Sokolina, October 29, 2007 (Oversize Folder 1)
    - Poster -- Student Research in the IAWA for Modernistic Architecture: Leanings and Gleanings [featuring Maria Rosaria Piomelli and Maria Auboeck-Karasz], undated (Box 11)
  - Public Relations, 1985-2007
    - Clippings, Bliznakov, 1985-1986, undated (Box 5)
    - Clippings, IAWA in publications, (4 folders), 1987-1991, 1999-2002, 2007 (Box 5)
    - IAWA brochure, (2 folders), 1991-1993 (Box 5)
    - IAWA promotional postcards (Box 5)
    - Various exhibit catalogs, brochures, handouts, related to the IAWA (Box 5)
  - Reference Files, 1985-2001
    - Architecture Cybercole Project, College of Architecture and Urban Studies, CD, Fall 1999 (Box 5)
    - Compiled address lists, A.I.A., U.I.F.A., and various other organizations, (2 folders), 1985-1986, and undated (Box 5)
    - Literature/Resources about women in architecture, Art + Architecture Library, Virginia Tech, 2001 (Box 5)
    - Newsletters from various organizations, 1989-1991 (Box 5)
    - Taliesin Fellowship Directory, Alumni and membership, 1932-1987 (Box 5)
- Archivist Files, 1973-2007 (Bulk, 1985-2007)
  - Administrative Files, (16 folders), 1985-2007 (Box 6)
  - Collection Development, 1974-1994 (Bulk, 1985-1994)
    - Books
      - Book requisitions about women in architecture, 1991 (Box 6)
      - Books in Special Collection about women in architecture, 1992 (Box 6)
    - Collection inventories, 1987, 1990, 1994, and undated (Box 6)
    - Compiled collection development materials (2 folders), 1974-1990 (Box 6)
    - Correspondence with potential donors, 1988 (Box 6)
    - Donors
      - AIA exhibit "That Exceptional One" (Box 6)
      - Chadeayne, Olive, 1992 (Box 6)
      - Dows, Wena, 1990 (Box 6)
      - Johnson, Jane C. Hall, 1990 (Box 6)
      - Koller-Buchweiser, Helene, 1990 (Box 6)
      - Leviseur, Elsa, 1990-1994 (Box 6)
      - Pfeiffer, Alberta, 1987-1992 (Box 6)
      - Schroeder, Han, 1988-1993 (Box 6)
      - Torre, Susana, 1990 (Box 7)
        - Torre interview, 3.5" diskette (Box 7)
      - Willis, Beverly, 1988-1992 (Box 7)
      - Wilson, Zelma, 1990-1991 (Box 7)
      - Zimbler, Liane, 1987-1988 (Box 7)
    - Mailings/Mailing Lists
      - Virginia Tech, College of Architecture, Alumnae, 1875-1979 (Box 7)
      - Architecture Schools, directory and responses, [mailings sent to architecture schools throughout the United States requesting female alumni directories for their architecture schools] (6 folders), 1987 (Box 7)
      - State Architectural Registration Boards, directory and responses, [mailings sent to architecture registration boards throughout the United States requesting the names of female architects registered within the state] (7 folders), 1987 (Box 8, Box 7)
      - International Architectural Associations, directories and responses, [mailings sent to various international architectural associations requesting the names of female architects registered with the organization], 1987-1988
        - Hermandad Nacional de Prevision Social de Arquitectos Superiores H Lista de Arquitectos de Espana, 1985-1986 (Box 8)
        - History of Women Architects Catalog, 1986-1987 (Box 8)
        - Royal Australian Institute of Architects Membership Directory, 1986 (Box 8)
        - United Architects of the Philippines Directory of General Membership, 1986 (Box 8)
        - The Hong Kong Institute of Architects Register of Membership, 1986-1987 (Box 8)
        - Schweizerischer Ingenieur- und Architekten-Verein Offizielles Mitglieder-Verzeichnis, 1986-1987 (Box 8)
        - Union of Hungarian Architects Membership Directory, 1988 (Box 8)
        - Arquitectas de Puerto Rico, El Caribe y la Florida, 1991 (Box 8)
      - Virginia Tech Faculty Roster, College of Architecture and Urban Studies, 1991-1993 (Box 8)
    - Potential donors listing, 1987-1989 (Box 8)
    - Slides and negatives of materials in the IAWA (Box 8)
  - Correspondence, 1984-1999
    - General Correspondence, 1985-1988 (Box 8)
    - IAWA Board members, 1988-1991 (Box 8)
    - Incoming mail, 1984-1999 (Box 8, Box 9)
    - Outgoing mail, 1987-1993, 1995-1997 (Box 8, Box 9)
  - Grants, 1988-1990
    - American Institute of Architects Foundation Grant and Account, 1989-1990 (Box 9)
    - General grant material, 1988-1989 (Box 9)
  - IAWA Biographical Database, (5 folders), 1989, 1994-1996, 2002-2005, 2007 (Box 9)
  - IAWA Newsletter, production, 1989-1992 (Box 9)
  - IAWA Website, 1995 (Box 9)
  - Publications, 1991-1992
    - Smith, Laura Katz. "The International Archive of Women in Architecture." Feminist Collections, vol. 12, no.4, Summer 1991, March 1991 (Box 9)
    - Smith, Laura Katz. "The International Archive of Women in Architecture: Preserving the History of the Invisible Partner." Art Reference Services Quarterly, vol. 1(2) 1993., 1991-1992 (Box 9)
  - Reference Files, 1979-2007 (Bulk, 1984-2007)
    - Architecture Libraries, information about their collections, 1988-1990 (Box 10)
    - Archival Collections of and about women architects in depositories in the United States, 1989 (Box 10)
    - Biographical Information, Esther McCoy, 1985-1990 (Box 10)
    - Definitions of Architectural Terms, 1984-1989 (Box 10)
    - Frank Lloyd Wright apprentices, 2004, 2007 (Box 10)
    - Lesbian Herstory Archives, 1979-1991 (Box 10)
    - Literature about women in architecture, (6 folders), 1973-1992, 1994-1996, 1998, and undated (Box 10)
    - Research Articles, (2 folders), 2002-2005 (Box 10)
  - Related Professional Organizations, 1983-2003
    - American Institute of Architects (AIA), 1983-1991 (Box 10)
    - Canadian Centre for Architecture, 1999 (Box 10)
    - International Union of Women Architects (UIFA), Washington, D.C., 1988 (Box 10)
    - Society of American Archivists, Architectural Records Roundtable, Survey, 2003 (Box 10)